Hello and welcome back to Python, Core and Applied Concept for Reliable Letters, Science
Workflow.
So, in today's this video we will continue our discussion of Bind Research Tree and we
will talk about some of the drawbacks of working with Bind Research Tree.
If you recall in the last lecture we discussed how to create Bind Research Tree from scratch
and how to then populate Bind Research Tree by adding element 1 at a time right and we
also have written one function which was actually adding this thing.
So, this BST insert was the function that we discussed in the last class, this BST insert
was helping us insert new values inside a existing Bind Research Tree and we experimented
with this function and we saw the function was working correctly.
But one thing which I noted very slightly in the previous lecture was that the overall
structure of the BST will depend upon the order in which you add this element because
the very first element becomes the root element of the BST.
Now, that may cause trouble and depending upon if the order in which element comes is
not favorable, we may end up with Bind Research Tree which are actually not balanced and
one of the major advantage of BST as we discussed in the last lecture was that if the BST
is balanced then searching in a BST for a value takes far less time right because you
either only search in the left half or the right half depending upon how the value compares
with the root node and in this way you can reduce our space by half in each go right
and that somehow leads to log and complexity of search as well as insert for searching
or inserting inside this BST, if the BST is balanced then you just need log and time
for doing both this activity where N is the number of nodes because log N becomes the
height of the BST. So, think about it in your free time and try to justify why for a balanced
Bind Research Tree, the height of the Bind Research Tree is always less log N of
where N is total number of elements in the Bind Research Tree. So, that's the major advantage
I mean of using BST that if your BST is balanced then you can do both insertion as well as search
which are most common activity on any data structure in log and time and log and doing being
being able to do it in log and time is a very huge advantage. It was not the case with not
let data structure which were linear in nature and we could get these advantages because
BST has this order property and also I mean in the good cases when your BST is balanced your
height is not only log N. So, losing these two are a very nice combination and that your tree
has a height of log N and your tree has this property where your root node is always better than
the element which is present in the left subtree and also your root node is
less than all the elements that is present in the right subtree. So, you can combine these two
property very nicely and come up with no efficient algorithm to search inside a Bind Research
Tree as well as no update Bind Research Tree by inserting some element into it. But when this
property of the BST this property of being balanced remember the property of being balanced is
not a mandatory property for Bind Research Tree right we had only two essential property for
BST one was this structural property which somehow guarantees that every node in the
BST can have at most two children and the other property was this ordering property. So,
so the balanced properties I mean if let us say we can define somehow this balance factor or
this balancing thing that you typically we are talking about. So, that is not a prerequisite
or not a requirement at least for the Bind Research Tree right. For example,
assume that if you have only two elements in your Bind Research Tree right so either one
element will be less than the other or the greater than other right I mean they
they assume that they are distinct element then your binary tree will be either you know right
skewed or left skewed right it it can never be balanced. So, you can never you know ensure
complete balance in your Bind Research Tree but then we want to define some notion of you know
balanced by in research tree and think about you know this kind of you know problematic
instances where tree make it you know unbalanced. So, let us talk about that you know in in
context of some you know example with some concrete example so that it makes sense. So,
this is the you know problem that I was talking about that depending on how these elements are
added into BST your BST may become completely you know unbalanced and then the height of the
BST is no more log of log and right where n is number of element in the BST. To give you a very
quick example I mean you can maybe apply the same function or that we have written BST insert
and then insert values in your Bind Research Tree where you know you start your you know your
Bind Research Tree your root is less than none in the beginning and then you add element in this
order. If you add elements in this order it is not difficult to you know convince yourself that
your tree will be skewed like this towards the right hand side right why because the first
element that you add is 10. So, 10 becomes the root node and then the 20 is the next element it
is greater than 10. So, it goes towards the right hand side okay. So, your node tree is not
at the current you know position when you insert this 20 is already skewed towards right but no
since you know every other value that is no coming is greater than the previous value you keep
on you know adding those element at the right hand side of the you know last element or to
not that you have added right and this way the tree keeps growing only towards the right hand
side right and and if you now measure the height of this tree it is no more log n right it is
exactly n right. So, these are extreme cases but you know this kind of a stream cases may occur
either you know completely you know these extreme cases are somewhere in in in between I mean
you may have some element which can get you balanced tree but then some at a stress you may get
something like this which can cause you know imbalance in some part of the tree. So, it's not
you know by just no maintaining the BST property you know in a nutshell what I'm trying to
emphasize is that no by just maintaining the BST property we cannot be sure that our binary
substrate that we get is always balanced okay and this kind of thing this kind of trees
are you know unbalanced tree I mean this is what we call unbalanced tree okay and very you know
go you know clean example is this you know increasing you know sorted let's say at least I mean if
you if your element comes in this you know sorted out either in increasing order or in decreasing
order right because if these elements come in decreasing order then in you can guess that
this tree will become now left skewed right because you know everything in the very beginning you
will get 50 and then 40 30 20 and 10 and all the new up no let us know members actually get to
the left subtree okay and that way the tree may also grow towards the left hand side okay.
So, in these kind of you know extreme example your tree is completely you know skewed I mean
and this is just one of the same thing that I mentioned right now so if you know run this code
which was you know our actual code okay so maybe we need to compile our code once more this BST
so we define it somewhere yeah here so let me compile this BST insert and after
this block if you again in that block on this sorted no list which represents you know the
bad kind of order in which so this order then you can see that the tree produce will be
okay so let me you know again compile the display tree function which we have this defined
earlier in the earlier class right I mean so this was BST insert and where is this display tree
so this is the code once we compile
no maybe we just compile the code for this display function even once we compile it
and then we come back to the place where we wanted to use it for the sorted list
okay so now we have both the functions compile and it should actually run okay now if you run on
this you can see you know when your input are in increasing order only you know any just step
what is happening your you know right child is not being updated okay and you know at the end
I mean what you get is this right child you know so left child remains none right and always the
right child is expanded into another you know tree where again the left child is none and then
right child has some value so you know so in picture I mean you know if you want to see this is
exactly the scenario right where your tree is balanced towards the right and side so we certainly
don't want this kind of you know scenario right where your tree becomes skewed in nature either
left skewed or not right skewed so we want to avoid it otherwise we will not get the benefit of
using BST kind of structure okay so this is what we know call no balancing okay so for
for example and this is you know somewhat balanced tree but this is no completely unbalanced tree
but we need and and when we have balanced tree then this is what we have right our height is
log of n where n is total number of nodes in the tree and if your height is in log of n then you
can do no most of the operation in of the order of log and time but if your tree grows you know in an
unbalanced way for example this way the height becomes of the order of n and then any activity
or any operation that you want to do on this data structure like you know insert or search
takes this log and so this you know of the order of n time so this this may have no real world
consequences and when your I mean these are some of the examples where you actually no real data
may have this sorted property and in that case if you want to store then using BST then you will
get this kind of skewed BST and you will not get the benefit of BST so what is the root cause
regular BST don't care about their shape right so they have some structural requirement right
structural requirement was that every node has should have at most not to children right and
that was only structural requirement but that does not in in force in any way for these trees
to be you know balanced right because in this case I mean it followed that is structural requirement
if you see closely right none of the node has more than two children but it was not balanced
right it was a skewed tree so so we need you know now somehow another no restriction or you can
say invariant that we want to maintain for this data structure which is what we call no balance
factor okay now so that's why you know we are going to discuss today something which is an
you know improvement over by necessity which we call height balance tree okay so there are
multiple ways in which you can you know balance height for this kind of binary substrate and we
will be discussing today one of the very you know popular height balance tree structure which is
called AVL tree okay so height balance tree maintains this extra property that for every node
the height of left and rights of tree differ by at most one okay so I will call my tree to be
height balanced only if this property is true right that no you're but in this case you can see
for example this is not height balance right because the right subtree has no height 4
but the left subtree had height 0 so I this will not qualify as no height balance tree but what
about this I mean can we say or something about this is it a height balance tree
for example for this node the left hand subtree has height 2 and the right hand subtree also has
height 2 right so for this node I mean this node will not complain right so this is not a
counter example to a height you know imbalance or let's hide balance right what about this node
for this node can we say the same okay there is no right child for this node 20 but there is a
left child okay but here also the no balance factor is only one right the difference in height
between left subtree and right subtree for this node is also one and if it is no one or less
than one then we don't care I mean we say that it's okay because anyway I mean if let's say
in the very the example that the simplest example that I gave you if you have only two elements
then you you can't know always say that no I can maintain a height difference of 0 between
node left and right right because one of the two will come as a left child or right child for
the simple or the simplest tree you will have high difference of one okay so what we say is we
don't worry if the height difference of the left subtree and the right subtree is one at any
you know place in our tree but if it is more than one then you know we would like to do something
so that you know we can correct this height imbalance okay so let me yeah let me come to
so this is how we define the balance factor okay so we measure our balance using a simple
calculation which is no which we call balance factor and what is this balance factor that height
of left subtree minus height of right subtree okay and the valid values for the balance
factor is no minus 1 0 or plus 1 so what we say essentially say that no if the height of the
left subtree and right subtree are same for a node let's say then it's perfectly alright but if
it is not let's say same I can accept a difference of one at max so this is no essentially what we
are saying okay and I had to allow that no difference of one because of that no simple case which I
mentioned right where we have only two element and we cannot actually do anything with those two
element but two no we have to actually allow this you know difference of one okay so so valid
values values for this balance factor is minus 1 0 and plus 1 and remember that no this balance
factor so these valid values has to be true for every node in the tree okay it's not like I mean
we are talking about only the root node maybe for root maybe I mean there may be you know some
special cases of BST where root node is not complaining because it's left no subtree and right
subtree has the same height but some somewhere down the line I mean there may be a no height
imbalance okay so we have to check this for every node in the you know binary surgery and if
this invariant is true for every node in the binary surgery then only we will call that binary
such to be a balanced no height balance tree okay for example I mean a very quick example let me
know increase the font of this so that no things are a bit clear okay now so this is a very you know
a small example to show you how can we calculate the balance factor okay so when we talk about
no this E and D since no they are anyway the leaf node the last node they don't have left
child alright child so these nodes can never be you know reason for imbalance in your tree okay so
at least I mean you can be sure about the leaf node but what if I go just one to the parent of
the leaf node okay so so again I mean C is the parent for this you know leaf node E and what is
the height of the left subtree on C there's nothing right so we say that the height is no zero
here the left subtree but what about the height of the right subtree is one right I mean because no
E is there so now if you take the difference of left subtree minus right subtree and try to
calculate the balance factor for this particular node C what do you get so zero minus one gives you
minus one right so C C's no balance factor is minus one so C will also not complain right because
we will allow one difference in in in the height of left subtree and right subtree okay so what
about B I mean if you calculate the balance factor of B what will you get now left subtree has
a height one but the right there is no right subtree here right I mean so the height of the right
subtree is zero so if you find the difference between the height of left subtree and right subtree
you will get a plus one okay so B as well as C both cannot complain because for both of them the
balance factor is actually plus one and minus one and which is allowed okay and also balance
factor of you know zero is allowed because that's the ideal case where you know both left subtree
and the right subtree has the same value or same height okay so what about A so if if you look
at A no the left subtree of A has a height two and the right subtree of height no A also has
height two so in this case also when we calculate the balance factor of A we get zero okay and this
is what we have summarized here right if we calculate this balance factor for each of the node
in the tree which can be no problematic except the no leaf node we figured out that the value for
each of these nodes where either zero one or minus one so if the value is for each of the node is
no either zero one or minus one we are happy we would say in this case that the
binary system is a balanced tree okay it's a height balance tree okay so this is a perfect you
know I mean this is perfectly alright from no the balance point of view or this balance factor
point of view because every node qualified our invariant or the no criteria that we put
for it to be a balanced tree but what about this tree I mean if you look at this I mean this
certainly looks like you know a skewed like left skewed binary system and you know by just
looking at it we would like to call it an unbalanced tree but can we figure out I mean which of
the node will complain and be the cause of the no unbalanced that is there in this tree okay so again
I mean with C there can't be any problem right because this is leaf node with B if you calculate
again there is a left tree which has height one but the right sub tree is missing so if you
know calculate the balance factor for this B we get plus one but in case of A if you calculate
again the balance factor there is nothing on the right but left sub tree has height two so if
you know calculate the difference the balance factor becomes plus two and this is the point I
mean this is the node that will now start company right because we could find out a node for which
the balance factor is not in this set no zero one or minus one no we we got a balance factor which
is plus two okay so this is the problematic node and hence we will not call this BST
a height balance no BST okay so this is the node which is causing the imbalance in the tree
okay so I hope I mean now you know it's clear to you what what is no balance factor and how to
calculate balance factor and how to figure out which which of the node may cause you know
may be the reason for a BST to not be a height balance by this is tree okay so now
no so if your tree is not you know balance then I mean we already discussed right this thing so
you can just read it so these are some of the drawback that you get and to counter this you know
difference in height of the left subtree and right subtree for any node we we thought we talk
about this height balance tree and there are three popular height balance tree which you can
know finding any other structure and algorithm book so they are known as avial tree red
black tree and B tree so what we discussed today is this avial tree you know we will discuss one
way to mitigate this on no imbalance in a binary search tree okay and that is the wire is no
avial tree so avial tree or nothing but binary search tree with an additional requirement that
the balance factor that we define just now for every node so the balance factor for any node in
the tree has to be you know one among these three values that plus one minus one or zero okay
so we will implement avial tree using you know the same dictionary and recursion pattern that
you already know in fact I am not going to implement this and this is going to be a you know
homework for you assignment for you so we will you know discuss about the idea of the height
avial height balance tree and different operations that you have to perform to balance the height
whenever there is an imbalance in height of the left subtree and the right subtree okay so let's
go directly to this avial tree concept and try to understand so what is it so an avial tree
is a self balancing binary search tree that we want to you know implement that maintains its
balance through automatic rotation so that we will discuss about an operation which is called
you know rotation no in the context of binary search tree and we will see that by doing these
rotations you can immediately get rid of this no imbalance okay so whenever you figure out
that some node is complaining because their balance factor has no went out of this set
or you know their balance factors no absolute value is greater than one in that case we will
immediately apply one of these rotations that we are going to discuss today and balance that tree
okay so it should have properties of you know BST so it should maintain the binary
such tree you know ordering invariant which says that no everything in the left subtree should be
less than the parent and everything on the right subtree should be greater than the parent it should
maintain this balance property that for every node this should be true so I mean to maintain
this balance property the tree data structure should be no self balancing what do you mean by
self balancing because if you want to maintain this you know balance property then you have to do
something beyond simple insertion the way we did in no binary search tree right because in binary
search tree we just figured out what is the correct position and we kept there but after an insertion
let's say an already balanced binary search tree may become no imbalance you you also need to check
whether this last insertion made my binary search tree imbalance and in that case if you figure out
that the no binary search tree now had become imbalance you need to do something to do something
to correct this imbalance that's what we call you know self balancing so this will be part of
every you know insert or delete an operation that you do on this kind of you know
white balance tree okay so this has to be taken care by those operations which tries to modify
this data structure okay so so let's you know quickly again revisit what what was the balance
factor so balance factor was height of less sub tree minus height of right subtree now I leave it
again as a homework to define this height function right because right now we are talking about height
in a intuitive way right we roughly understand what does a height mean for a tree but can you
also you know define a function to calculate this height no for a given tree so do that okay so
nitric that again as a no homework try to define this no height function which can calculate the
height of a given tree and then once you have that function you will also have a function to
calculate balance factor and we need to store the balance factor for each of the node because
you know we we want to maintain this invariant okay we already discussed it that no
a military always maintains the you know balance and if you can maintain the balance then you can
ensure that you know you can do all these no update and search operation on this no data
structure in out the order of log and you know time okay so this is again you know an example of
height balance tree because here I mean you can see that no all the node has been a balance factor
either you know zero or minus one or plus one so you can actually again revisit this
BST on your own and check whether this is a balanced BST now let's talk about know the some some
scenarios that can cause imbalance and in those scenario what can we do to let's say you know
recover from that imbalance and no make it balance okay so there are four types of rotation
that we will discuss just now which can help us regain the balance from an unbalanced tree okay so
so let's discuss them one by one okay so the very first type of rotation that we talk about
is called no left left rotation okay so
so so what is the scenario so for example I mean assume that initially your tree was no balanced
okay so this is again I mean a very simplistic example I mean this may not be the most general
case but somehow these four you know cases captured the general all possible scenario that might
happen in your actual BST that you are you know updating okay so let me talk about the very
simplistic case you know using the simplest kind of example where we first time encounter some
in imbalance so the very first case is the scenario where your node is left heavy and left child
is left heavy or balanced so what does it mean so to understand this no assume that initially you
had created a BST which had only A and B okay and B is on the left hand side of A or is B is a
left child of A okay so assume that your BST only has this no A and B initially so why did you
put B by the way on the left hand side as a left child of A because you know B had a value which
less than the value of A right so that that's the only reason why you would put B as a left child of A
and so at so at the time let's say another C arrived which has value even lesser than B
okay so till the point when you had only A and B in your tree was the tree
the unbalanced it was balanced so if you had only A and B you you say I mean your tree was not
unbalanced right because no for B it was not B you cannot complain and A will also not
complain why because the balance factor for A was 1 but as soon as you add a C which is no
less than you you have to insert C here because C's value is less than B so in that moment it's
itself so we will not complain but then A will start complaining okay so this is no the scenario
that you are inserting into the left subtree of the left child okay so initially if your tree was
you know balanced but if your current you know insertion is in the left subtree of the left child
then you might encounter this kind of situation right because the final place where you inserted C
is on the left subtree of A so initially it was balanced but then now it can become unbalanced
so right so I hope I mean this is clear why this is an unbalanced tree because for A if you
calculate the balance factor you can see the left child subtree has high 2 but there is nothing
on the right okay so the moment you insert C at that moment itself A will start complaining
right because for the first time balance factor went no beyond the allowed set of minus 1 0 and 1
okay so the moment we encounter such a scenario where you know this is the case that your
balance factor for the node becomes plus 2 so we can do something very simple to correct this
balance factor so can I convert this tree into this tree without violating any of the property of
BST if I can let's say do this I mean if let's say somehow you know one can transform this tree
into this bottom tree without violating the property of BST then I would be happy right because
then I will do this transformation and make the tree balance because you see one of the advantage is
that the bottom tree that you are seeing is a balanced tree right but if it is also a BST then
there should not be a issue right then I whenever I see such such a circumstances you know happening
I will immediately you know transform this kind of you know tree or subtree into this kind of tree
okay so why this is a valid transformation in this particular case so what have we done what we
say is now we make you know B parent and A the right child of B and see let with the left child
of B right so initially also if you see C was the left child of B right so it's same right so
there is C and B cannot complain with respect to each other why because anyway C's value was
less than you know B so C can happily sit on the left subtree of B but can A go to the right subtree
of B is it a problem or it's allowed since A was parent of B and B was the left child of A
you already know that the value of A must be greater than the value of B right because B is
sitting on the left hand side of left subtree of A so you know that the A's value is greater than
B so if A's value is greater than B the moment you make you know B parent and keep A on the right hand
side it should not complain right because this is a valid BST property right now according to the BST
ordering property this is allowed okay B can become parent of A when A is the right child of B
because you know BST says that everything on the right subtree should be greater than
the parent okay so transforming you know this tree into this tree
doesn't break the BST ordering property okay so at least it's not so if you transform this
you know this BST into this BST so then if you transform this tree or this BST into this tree
it's not breaking the you know ordering property so at least one of the ordering property one of
the essential property of the BST you could you know easily check that it's not being broken but
about the other property the other property was the structural property right so are we breaking
the structural property you know by you know transforming this tree into something like this
are we let's say you know introducing nodes for which there are more than two
child no right because no for each of the no you can see there are at most two children right so
neither we are breaking a structural property nor we are breaking the you know ordering property
right so if we are not doing if we are not breaking both then I will certainly transform it into
this form why because the advantage is by transforming you know this you know tree which was
troublesome due to this node which has a balance factor of plus two by transforming this into
this we actually get rid of that no balance factor problem now in this tree if you calculate
again the balance factor you will see that no balance factor for every node is within a
loud range of you know minus one zero and one okay so that's why you know this kind of transformation
you can easily do to recover from this kind of no imbalance that has been introduced by the last
insertion that happened here okay so this is what we call you know LL or you know right rotation so
why we are calling it right rotation rotation by the way because see I mean a
c b and a where in this form right and then a now comes to the right of b okay so this is no
like you know right you're rotating it in a from top to the right set I write I mean so so if you
can you know justify this name then it's good otherwise also it's okay I mean but I mean this
kind of thing is we call right rotation okay so so the second kind of you know rotation that
we use to get rid of this kind of you know imbalances what we call RR or left rotation okay so this
just the opposite case of the previous one that we have discussed again I mean assume that a b
we are already you know in your tree in this order so since they were in this order you know that
a was I had a value which is less than b at that time it did not complain but as soon as you
added a c it started complaining right why it started complaining because the balance vector of a
now becomes minus two so it's then you know you know it's not a balanced tree anymore
now with this kind of our tree can we transform this tree into this without breaking the BST
property and achieving balance right because to the one advantage you clearly see is that if you
can transform this into this you certainly you know now maintain the balance right because whatever
was causing imbalance you could get rid of that okay so if we are not breaking the BST property
both structural and ordering property then we should be happy and this this is perfectly
know doable thing right this kind of transformation you can easily do to maintain the
imbalance factor okay and you can convince yourself that this is again allowed right because
b and c are not changing their position with respect to each other right b was earlier also
parent of c now also b is parent of c the only thing that you did is that you made a now the left
child of b okay so if you make a left child of b is it allowed this is perfectly all right because
it was any way less than b so it can come in the left subtree of b okay so think about it
no again I mean in your free time and try to convince that this is a perfectly valid transformation
which maintains the BST property okay so by doing this kind of transformation you will not
break any of the essential property for you know BST okay so this is a second scenario
but I mean scenario can be no different than these two cases I mean and these two are again I
mean I'm trying to emphasize that these two are very simplistic cases in your general binary
such tree at the moment these you know height balance properties you know broken maybe more complex
and general than this but if you understand these things properly you can easily figure out what
kind of transformation you need to do in the most general case okay so the simplistic cases are
which you need to understand to understand the logic and once you understand the logic I leave it
as an exercise for you to think about the most general case in which know these kind of
imbalances may be introduced in your binary such tree and in that case I mean what will be
the suitable transformation that you will apply to get rid of no these kind of imbalances okay
so these are very simple cases so this is called right right rotation and you know you can see
that this is also no valid the third case will can be something like this okay where you are
introducing a C so I remember again AB will not complain when they are alone in the tree
but as soon as you insert a element C which is less than A but greater than B so C will now come
towards the right side of you know B right as in the right subtree of B remember this case three
is not same as you know case one right you were in the case one C was less than B so it came
toward to this end but right now what we are saying is although C was less than A so it went into
the left subtree but it was no greater than B so it came here right so this is the know the situation
when it can know happens like you know first right so if this is the case then can we
no recover from this kind of imbalance and again you can see that there is an imbalance
because for A the left subtree has high two but there is no right subtree so the imbalance
no or the balance factor is plus two so A will complain how to get rid of or you know this kind
of imbalance so we will say that we can get rid of this kind of imbalance in two steps
okay the very first step is you change the position of B and C with respect to each other
okay what we say is that you know instead of a B being parent of C now makes C parent of B
because this is what we call left no rotation the first rotation is left that you know you take
a C to the top and remove you know move B to the as a left child of C okay so again I mean is
it allowed I mean is it a valid thing to do if I do this kind of transformation will I break some
property now remember I mean if you just change the relative position of B and C A will not
complain right why because both B and C where smaller than A that's why they are on the left
subtree of A and even after the transformation they are on the left subtree of A right so A has no
problem right because no B C where earlier also on the left subtree now also B and C are on the
left subtree but what about B and C can C complain because now C is a no left child which is B
so the left child has to be less right it's value has to be less than C
so if that was the case then C should not complain right and was that the case
so if you see the previous no tree structure that was the case right that the value of B was
actually less than C so if the value of B was less than C then I can happily make C parent of B
and keep B no as the left child of C okay so again I mean it is not difficult to convince yourself
that we can transform this trade to this without breaking the BST property right both
structure and the ordering property okay but remember we did not achieve anything right because
here also if you see the balance factor for A will be plus 2 okay so by doing just this transformation
we could not get rid of this imbalance so we are still we are having non balanced tree
but once you do this operation we do a second rotation and that solves our problem okay
so in the second step what we say is now we apply a right rotation now you remember I mean
this is a familiar structure that you have already seen right AC and B all are in no left skewed
right I mean your tree is very simple right now and for this kind of imbalance we have already
a solution right remember this was the very first solution that we did right so for this kind
of scenario what we did was a right rotation right this is what we call right rotation so what
does what did we do we made the B the root and then push A to us right so this is why we call
right rotation okay so whatever was the root you just bring it to us the right hand side of B
so can we do that kind of right rotation here because we already you know or transform this into
something which we already fixed right we know how to fix this kind of thing so we just push A to
as a right child of C right so from here to here is what we already discussed and then this is
allowed right this is perfectly allowed but again I mean convince yourself by thinking
no slowly what this why this is allowed right because A was parent for C so certainly A was
greater than a value for of A was greater than C right because C is the left child of A the value
of A was greater than C then why can't A come on the right subtree of C and the moment you do
this transformation now you can see that wanted that this final tree is a balanced tree
okay so although not in one step but in two steps we can we could you know achieve a balanced
factor right which is desired it from here we went to this one which is certainly allowed we
have discussed why it is allowed and from here we went to this one which is again allowed
by the BST property and in this case now we also have you know balance so our tree is high
balance okay so so we can actually transform this into something like this without any problem
so this is the third scenario that something like this may you know happen in your
no modification of BST and when will it happen when when you're you're inserting something
into the right subtree of your left child okay so if let's say the last element that you are
trying to insert is onto the into the no right subtree of your left child of the tree then
this kind of thing might happen but then think carefully because no situation may not be as
simple as this because what we are saying is you're inserting C as the right subtree of B but
there may be something here also right and the C may not go immediately after B but somewhere
down the line right so that's the most general case I was referring from the very beginning
but I'm not giving you a complete explanation of what you should do in those kind of scenario scenario
think carefully and come up with a you know a nice way of dealing those general kind of scenario
but if you understand this simple transformation on this simple tree properly it should not be
you know difficult to come up with the exact logic logic for the most general case of BST okay
so think about this problem you know on your own and try to come up with the appropriate rotations
you know in in the in the most general you know setting of a BST okay so what about the last
the no scenario so last scenario is again you know just like the previous one but here you know
we have a balanced factor of minus two why because on the left hand side nothing is there
but in the right hand side we have something like this okay and if you have something like this
how to fix it again I mean you can maybe you know take a guess from the previous case that we
have seen can we transform this first into this kind of a structure okay so A will not complain
because for A nothing is changing but what about P and C so can we complain about C
so cell B complaint so for this tree to be a BST or what is required that C should be greater than
B that's how I mean she can come on as a right child of B but is C no greater than B already
so here C is already greater than B right so if I transform this into this even B should not
complain and C will not complain because he doesn't have any child okay so yeah so think about
this this case is carefully so these are you know four different types of rotation that we apply
on any you know balanced by by necessary to recover from this imbalance and you know get balance okay
so to get a balanced by necessary so yeah so these are the things that know we discussed today
so I leave as a assignment for you to you know define this rotation which we call left rotation
rotation and use them to you know correct the imbalance that is there in in your tree after
any insertion okay so for AVL tree now you have to write down all this code I mean you have
so the the idea or our final goal is to maintain an AVL tree now AVL tree are you know
by by necessary with this height balance thing you know check every time okay and for doing this
kind of height balancing you have to rotate left or right or a combination of both of this that
we have discussing in the previous no example using previous example so these are some you know
function for which I have given you signature and you are expected to implement this function
and submit it okay so what's the very first one is the rotate left okay and what it does it it
gets an unbalanced node okay so we we try to figure out what is the you know unbalanced node
and after getting to that unbalanced node we will try to do this kind of rotation to no left
rotation to get rid of no so what is rotate left in the above if you see so this is the left
rotation right so in this kind of no situation we want to implement this logic no of
transformation that we discuss here okay so think about it so rotate left and rotate right
right two functions which take an unbalanced node and does this so input is node or dictionary
that is right heavy so if it is right heavy it needs a no left rotation right no so returns
should be a new root node after the left rotation okay and this is exactly what we discussed
also write some similar function for right rotation okay and then can you
write a function which uses combination of this you know left rotation and right rotation
to balance a particular node let's see you could figure out that some node is a no imbalance
so so can you then write down a function which can convert that node into or know that part of
the tree into a balanced tree okay so the input is node dictionary that might be unbalanced
and the return for this return value for this you know function that you want to write is the
balanced node okay so again I mean so this this may be you know more complicated right because here
you have to identify first what kind of imbalance is there no which of these four you know cases
you are in and then depending upon what is your current no scenario you have to apply one of the
possible transformations or you know discuss transformation from above to solve these
imbalance okay so this is what I expect you to write down okay so again I mean these are some
no easy example to help you visualize this again same discussion that we had earlier so go
to know in an offline mode and try to come up with these signatures so so finally what I want
you to implement all these you know function signatures so I have summarized them so these are
some you know core function signature that you need to implement in order to implement this
no avial or high balance trees okay so first one is you know create node I mean can you write
down a function we just create a node you know creates and it turns a new avial node this study
then the second function is get height remember I mean now we can you know detect whether a node is
complaining or not by calculating only height right I mean if you don't have a function to get
height you cannot calculate balance factor and then you will never know whether a node is balance
or not okay so first write down that height function so this function you know get height to calculate
height for any node so think about it on your own and try to come up with an implementation
using this can you now you know implement a function which can tell you what is the balance
factor at each node okay so this this function should calculate balance factor
for any no given node that you passed this function okay and once you have this balance factor
you also have to maybe you know write a function which will update height right because whenever
you add so now you want to maintain this height information always in your dictionary so that
you immediately know whenever you know the balance factor for any of the node goes beyond the
allowed let's say range so can you also write this you know update height function so whenever
you add a node or remove a node from your there's a height balance tree so at that time so after
that no addition or removal you should be able to know update the height for each of the node in
the tree right so so so for that you would need a no update height function so either you integrate
this update height function when you are you know calling when you're you know modifying your data
structure or you can write down it separately and then you know call this whenever you are changing
your data structure okay so write down this update height function so so that now this this
takes a node and then again based on its children I mean it can actually update the height of
the parent node then write this rotate left function which I've already not discussed so it
it should take an unbalanced node and try to do this left rotation to fix the you know
this kind of you know imbalance so similarly rotate right you have to write down so once you have
rotate left and right or maybe now you you are in a position to know insert node right because once
you insert node so after the insert and you may figure out that you know there is an imbalance
introduced and at that time you may have to use this left and right rotation in combination with
each other to to you know get rid of that imbalance so again I mean read the signature of this
function carefully and try to implement this on your own then I mean this is a simple
search function that you might have written for you know BST you have to again write that here
and there are some utility function but these are optional I mean if you want to skip you can
skip this function but at least right know all the implementation of these functions for which I
provided you signature here no until this no section 4 okay so with this I would like to conclude
no today's lecture so in today's you know video we briefly discussed about this idea of height
balance tree and we we we we we we discuss why this is important and we also discuss about
the overall logic of maintaining the height I mean if there is an temporary imbalance that has
been introduced by insertion of a new element or deletion of existing element okay so we talked
about LLLR and you know this left-right combination kind of rotation which can help us get rid of
this kind of imbalances what do you I expect from you is to write down complete implementation of
the function signature that I have given for you know this lecture so I will meet you in the
next lecture so until then goodbye thank you